Sometimes when running a query, we only want to
see a value once because we may be trying to see
how many values of a column are in a table. For
example, I have a very small query set to list
product IDs from the Production.ProductCostHistory
table. I will execute it, and we have
395 rows, but notice that we have many duplicates.
I only want to see each product ID once.
The keyword DISTINCT will accomplish
this. I will add the word DISTINCT
after SELECT and execute this again. Now we only
have 293 rows, meaning 293 products have a cost
history. Let's see what happens if I add
the StandardCost column to this query.
We are back up to 395 rows, meaning that there
are 395 distinct combinations of a product ID
and a standard cost, and this also tells us
there are no duplicates of a product ID and
cost since we saw 395 product IDs originally. The
takeaway here is that DISTINCT means a distinct
occurrence of a combination of values for
all of the columns specified in a query.